Hi, this doctor
is Zwei Bell, and
today we'll be talking
about disorders
of fluid balance
and hypernatremia.
We'll cover a few
different objectives.
First, by the end
of this lecture,
you'll be able to explain
water balance
within the body.
Next, you'll be
able to illustrate
the pathophysiology of
hypernatremia
and hypovolemia.
You'll be able to
differentiate the
causes of hypernatremia
and hypovolemia.
You'll be able to
illustrate how to diagnose
and treat hypernatremia.
And finally, we
will be able to explain
diabetes insipidus.
A couple of questions
to get us started.
First, how much of
the total body water
is located within the
intracellular fluid?
The correct answer
here is D, 67% or two
-thirds of total body
water is intracellular,
which means that 35
% is extracellular.
And only 10% is
actually intravascular
or plasma water.
So only 10
% is actually
within our vessels.
Next, excretion or
retention of electrolyte
-free water by the
kidneys is modulated
through which the
following hormones t3
oxytocin epinephrine
or antidiuretic hormone
the correct
answer here is
antidiuretic hormone
which we'll be
discussing further
in this lecture
it's instructive to
look at the capillary
on the arterial end we
have a net filtration
pressure of plus 10.
that means the fluid's
exiting the capillary
since the hydrostatic
pressure, which is
about 35 mmHg, is
greater than the blood
colloidal osmotic
pressure of 25 mmHg,
so thus net filtration.
Mid-capillary, we
reach equilibrium,
so there's actually
no net filtration
with the hydrostatic
and the colloidal
pressures being
equal at 25 mmHg.
On the venous end,
we have reabsorption
with a net filtration
pressure of minus
seven millimeters
in mercury so that's
because the capillary
hydrostatic pressure
is less than the blood
colloidal pressure
so as we reviewed in
that question earlier
water balance is
maintained by antidiuretic
hormone which goes by
a couple other names,
arginine
vasopressin, ABP,
or simply vasopressin.
This is synthesized
in the magnocellular
neurons of the
hypothalamus and
is released from
the pituitary gland.
Now, ADH exerts a
few effects that are
noteworthy. Through
concurrent multiplication,
antidiolite
hormone stimulates
active sodium
chloride reabsorption
in the thick
ascending limb.
There is passive
countercurrent multiplication
with an ADH-stimulated
reabsorption
of urea in the
medullary collecting
duct. There is water
reabsorption in the
descending limb that
concentrates luminal
sodium chloride and
allows sodium chloride
diffusion at the
thin descending limb.
If we look at the
collecting duct, we
see that vasopressin
is regulating water
permeability, right?
So vasopressin
binds the type 2
vasopressin receptor,
as you see in the
diagram as V2R.
Once it binds to
V2R and the basilar
membrane of the principal
cells, it's going
to activate adenyl
cyclase. Adenyl cyclase
is then going to
increase cyclic AMP
and stimulate protein
kinase A activity.
From there, the
cytoplasmic vessels carry
aquapor two water channel
proteins and insert
them into the luminal
membrane as a response
to vasopressin
adh this is what's
increasing the water
permeability so really those
aquaporin two water
channels are increasing
the water permeability
for the collecting
dough when vasopressin
simulation ends
these water channels
are actually retrieved
from it by an endolytic
process and water
permeability returns
to the low basal rate.
Here's just another
diagram of what's
happening in the
kidneys, multiple levels,
multiple sites. It's
also a nice overview
to remind us where
we are in the setting
of water filtration
and water balance.
Now we're going to talk
about water balance.
One area where
this affects us
clinically is
hypovolemia or
lack of volume
in the patient.
And this is really
broken down into two
categories that help
us differentiate
where the hypovolemia
is coming from.
And this is meaning
that there's
either renal causes
of hypovolemia or
extra renal causes
of hypovolemia.
And we could really
understand this
better in a
clinical scenario,
which we're going
to run through.
So we have Mr. R.
He's an 80-year
-old nursing home
resident with
a history of
severe dementia.
He's brought to the
emergency department
with lethargy and
confusion, and serum
chemistries reveal
a sodium of 168.
So 80-year-old,
severe dementia, we're
in emergency
department lethargy and
confusion and an
elevated sodium level
so by definition we're
talking about
hypernatremia
hypernatremia is any
sodium concentration
greater than 145
millimoles per week
hypernatremia is
really a manifestation
of a disease or
other disorder
in body fluid
maintenance right so
it's a a sign that
we're seeing not
usually the cause
of what's going on
it's less common than
hyponatremia but much
more deadly there's
mortality rates as
high as 40 to 60
percent depending on the
research and literature
you're looking at
When you're thinking
about a patient
with hypernatremia,
there's key
things that you want
to think about as
part of your
differential diagnosis.
So there's really
three main situations.
First is impaired water
intake or not consuming
enough water for a
variety of reasons.
There is a hyperglycemic
hyperosmolar state.
And finally, there's
diabetes insipidus.
From a physiological
standpoint,
hypernatremia and
hyperosmolar states are
potent stimulators of
antidiuretic hormone.
So not causing the
body diurese, not lose
water and thirst,
which makes perfect
sense, right? We're
thirsty, so your body
wants to consume more
water because there's
not not enough of
it and your body is
not excreting water
through urine as
potentiated by adh so
this is going to promote
drinking and hypernatremia
occurs due to
unawareness of thirst or
unable to attain water
a few key demographic
populations
are more likely to be
impacted by
hypernatremia infants
elderly patients uh
really those with severe
dementia as we saw with
mr r in our clinical
scenario half of
patients half the elderly
patients actually
have a superimposed
process so comorbid
conditions that's happening
acutely so think like
uta ****** pneumonia
and as we said before,
30-day mortality
rate as high as 41.5%.
So it really varies,
but a pretty high
clinical mortality rate
no matter where you're
looking. And that's
why it's so important
to be aware of what's
going on and how to
treat this effectively.
From a pathophysiology
perspective, water
is lost through
insensible water loss.
If you're increasing
your water for an acute,
or if you're increasing
your water loss
from, for an acute
process, such as diarrhea.
We also see it when
it's not matched
by oral intake.
So hypernatremia
develops and our
kidneys are really
maximizing water
absorption, right?
So nothing we
haven't said already
hypernatremia with
marked hyperglycemia this
is what happens when
we have an osmotic
diuresis resulting in
free water loss usually
there's an altered
sensorium and patients are
not taking in as much
water and that can
result in hypernatremia
the magnitude of how
severe this is actually
often hidden by initial
labs so the mechanism
this works is
hyperglycemia pulls water
from the intracellular
fluid to the extracellular
fluid so it's
actually diluting the
sodium concentration
clinically how will
these patients present to
us so some things to
note in patients with
dehydration, you're
going to see tachycardia,
orthostatic hypotension,
and dry mucous membranes.
If we look at the
sensitivity and specificity,
the absence of
tachycardia does not
mean that your patient
is not dehydrated.
However, if
the patient is
tachycardic, that
means they are
likely suffering
from dehydration.
Decreased skin
turgor is one that's
particularly
useful as it's both
fairly sensitive
and specific.
When we get to
the presence of
hypernatremia, in
addition to dehydration,
we get some
neurologic defects.
So actually we
can get some
focal defects, seizures,
altered sensorium.
Now, going back
to our patient,
Mr. R, if we're
going to evaluate his
differential diagnosis,
we talked about
three different
categories where a
patient will become
hypernatremic, right?
So someone who's not
consuming enough water,
someone who's
hyperglycemic, and someone
who's suffering from
diabetes insipidus.
In this case, our
leading hypothesis is
going to be inadequate
water consumption.
Why is that?
Well, we know that
he's elderly and
has a history
of neurologic
disability, right?
He has severe dementia,
something to look
for in patients,
is a concomitant illness.
And this patient
will likely appear
hypotensive and
tachycardic. Something we
wouldn't want to miss
is if the patient's
suffering from
hyperglycemia. which
is the cause of
their hypernatremia.
If this was the case,
the patient would
likely have diabetes
mellitus, right?
What we'll see
in our test is a
markedly elevated
serum glucose.
Whereas if the
patient's suffering from
not consuming enough
water, the glucose
likely would be normal,
possibly slightly
elevated, but it
would not be severely
elevated like we'd
see in hyperglycemia.
Another important
thing to note that
we should also be
thinking about is
diabetes insipidus,
which I've been
hinting at, but we'll
cover in greater
detail later on
in this lecture.
But a key differentiation
of diabetes
insipidus is
that the urine
osmolality will be
low. And in a patient
with inadequate
water consumption,
the urine osmolality
will be high.
Now, so if we go
back to our patient,
Mr. R, and we look
at his examination,
we see that his
blood pressure
is indeed normal.
He is tachycardic
with a pulse of 110
beats per minute,
mildly elevated
temperature at
100.6, respiratory
rate is 20,
oral mucose is parched,
axilla is dry.
so dry mucous membranes
as we know it before.
Lung exam is
difficult because
the patient's
not putting a lot
of effort into
his deep breaths.
Cardiac exam, neck
veins are flat,
so another sign
of dehydration.
On lab studies,
as we know from the
beginning of this case,
the patient's
hypergenic right at 168.
Potassium is normal.
Bicarbonate, normal.
Chloride, elevated.
BUN, elevated at 45.
Creatinine is normal.
And serum glucose
is slightly
elevated at 110.
So not that severe
elevation we'd see
in hyperglycemia.
So our leading hypothesis
for this clinical
scenario should still
be hypernatremia
due to inadequate
water intake, right?
And the reason we're
seeing this often is
a superimposed illness
that could worsen
cognitive function.
And we want to make
sure this is an evidence
-based diagnosis,
right? Confirmed
by hypernatremia,
increased urine
osmolality, and
the absence of
hyperglycemia. In
terms of making the
diagnosis, Mr. R's urine
osmolality is 950
milliosmoles per liter.
Normal is 580.
And we get a chest X
-ray because as we know,
it oftentimes inadequate
water can happen
with incontinence
illness, right? So the
chest X-ray is going to
reveal, in this case,
a lower lobe pneumonia,
right lower lobe.
And blood culture is
showing strep pneumonia.
So we have a bacterial
pneumonia at this point.
We've identified
the cause.
We know what's going
on. Now what should
we do? How do we
correct it? How do we
fix the hypernatremia
in this patient?
And how do we treat
the underlying
cause of the patient's
hypernatremia?
Doing both is
really important.
We're going to go
through how to collect
or correct the water
deficit and how you
determine how much
fluid that we should be
providing to patients
now this is not something
not something you
need to memorize it's
not something you're
going to be calculating
on your exam this is
something for your
understanding for
the concept of how we
calculate and how to
treat hypernatremia
we want you to
understand how to provide
adequate fluid replacement
in these patients
And I think it's
instructive to
understand why and
how we determine that.
So the first thing we
do is calculate the
patient's water
deficit, how much water
the body is down from
its baseline state,
and you can see the
formula on this slide.
And just to use an
example, if we had
a middle-aged 60
-kilogram woman who has
a serum sodium
concentration of 168,
total body water
is about 50%, and
the water deficit
can be approximated.
So if your total body
water is 50% of the
patient's body weight,
which is, you know,
something we can do as
a standard calculation,
we can calculate that
160 over 140 minus 1,
and we multiply
that by the
product of 0.5 times 60.
So, our water deficit
in this case winds
up being 6 liters
when we simplify this
equation. So, a 6
-liter water deficit.
The next thing
we need to figure
out is how much
we're going to
change our serum
sodium by the fluid
we're infusing
into the patient.
So, for example,
if the fluid
we're infusing
into this patient,
the way we calculate
this is the sodium
concentration of the
infusate minus the
patient serum sodium
and we divide that
by the total body
water plus one so
one common type of
fluid is five percent
dextrose in water
which we call d5w and
as you would expect
there's no sodium
So the infusate
sodium would be zero.
If we're looking
at normal sodium,
it's a 0.9 serum
sodium concentration.
So that would equal
154. So for this
patient, if we were
to give D5W and we
calculate out the
change in serum sodium
that we'd see on the
bottom, that would
mean we would lose 5.4
millimoles of sodium.
So that would be 5
.4 millimole sodium
decrease in the
patient's sodium
concentration for
one liter of D5W.
So we can expect
the patient's sodium
would drop by 5
.4 for every liter
of D5W we give
to this patient.
Importantly, one
thing we haven't
mentioned yet is our
goal. And our goal is
to reduce the patient
serum sodium by
four to six
milliequivalents per liter.
And you do not, do
not want to exceed
10 milliequivalents
per liter in a 24
-hour period. So that's
really important.
So if we're trying
to correct six
milliequivalents per
liter of sodium over a
24-hour period, and
one liter of D5W,
as we mentioned,
is going to make a
change of 5.4
milliequivalents of sodium.
We want to infuse
1.1 liters of D5W.
However, we also
need to look at how
much obligatory
water loss is, right?
That happens over the
normal cost of a day,
and we need to replace
those as well. So we
usually use 1 to 1.5
of obligatory water
loss. And therefore, in
this patient, we would
calculate, we give 2
.5 liters of water in
24 hours of D5W to
correct the serum sodium.
So again, the numbers
here are not important.
You're not going to
have to calculate this.
There's calculators
you can use when you're
a resident intern and
a practicing physician.
What's really important
is to understand
what affects these,
how they're calculated.
And the key
takeaway is that you
want to correct by 4
to 6 milliequivalents
per liter, not
exceeding 10.
And that is
really important
for your patient's care.
So for Mr. R, the
patient we were talking
about before, we want
to correct his serum
sodium giving d5w we
calculate the free water
administration we
provide to calculate it
by four to six
milliequivalents per liter
over 24 hours we
give him piperacillin
tazobactam to treat his
pneumonia and three days
later this patient's
electrolytes turn
normal his neurologic
function returns and
ultimately this patient
is discharged to a
skilled nursing facility
with oral antibiotics
key things take
away here we treat
the underlying
cause and we
corrected the
patient serum sodium
we corrected the
patient serum sodium by
looking at the total
body water and the type
of fluid we administer
and treating the
underlying cause is
critically important
that we noted earlier
on the x-ray now let's
look at a different
clinical scenario so
a 79 year old female
also with dementia,
although mild,
and presents with
worsening confusion
for 48 hours.
She's a nursing home
patient and being
treated with a UTI
with antibiotics.
You don't have a lot
of information when
she presents to the
emergency department.
She's otherwise been
healthy, takes no
other medications.
So 79-year-old
female, recent UTI,
worsening confusion,
vital signs.
She has no fever,
although her temperature
is slightly elevated
at 100.1. Pulse is
normal. Respiratory rate
is normal. Blood pressure
is fine. She is
disoriented, lethargic.
Heart, lung, abdomen,
unremarkable. You do
note that she has poor
skin turgor and dry
mucous membranes which
if you recall are
signs of dehydration
her serum sodium is high
and her plasma osmolality
are high as well
and she has a decreased
urine osmolality
what's happening
here is a common
presentation of
diabetes and syptis
the issue is water
excessive water excretion
our patient earlier
mr r had inadequate
water consumption this
patient is not having
an issue consuming water
but instead an issue
with excreting too
much water the body's
not holding on to it
and this happens due to
a decrease in or
resistance to anti-diuretic
hormone adh causes
the urine to constrate
therefore, increasing
our total body water.
But in these patients,
ADH isn't working.
So therefore,
we're going to see
a dilute urine in
these patients.
So diabetes insipidus
characterized
by a high plasma sodium
concentration, an increased
plasma osmolality,
and a low urine
osmolality.
Therefore, these
patients are dehydrated
and they have a low
urine osmolality.
Now, you would
expect that the
body was
functioning properly
for the urine
osmolality to
be high in these patients
because the
body would want
to hold on to the water.
But in this case,
there's a lot
of water in the
urine, so the
body is not acting
appropriately,
and therein
lies the issue.
Now, there's two
different types
of diabetes
insipidus. There's
central and
nephrogenic DI.
In central diabetes
insipidus, there is
a deficient secretion
of ADH. So not
enough ADH is being
secreted by the body.
In contrast,
nephrogenic diabetes,
as we get from the
name, is based in the
kidney adh is being
secreted appropriately
however there's
renal resistance to
anti-diuretic hormone
so the anti-diuretic
hormone is not working
properly in the
kidneys and that's
why we lose water
lithium specifically can
cause the aquaporin
water channel dysfunction
which we talked
about earlier in the
collecting ducts so
lithium is a common
cause of nephrogenic
diabetes insipidus
central diabetes
insipidus some common
causes oftentimes it's
idiopathic however
head trauma is a
common one cns tumors
infections like
meningitis cva strokes so
something typically
going on in the brain.
Nephrogenic causes
are pretty different.
As we mentioned,
lithium is one of
the more common
ones, amphotericin B,
sidofovir, which is
an HIV medication.
So patients
taking sidofovir
for HIV can also
have diabetes,
nephrogenic
diabetes insipidus.
We see congenital
causes. So if there's a
defect of aquaporin-2
water channels, again,
this is going to
cause nephrogenic
DI. We can see it
in amyloidosis,
sarcoidosis, and
lupus as well.
So how do we
determine whether this
is a central
diabetes insipidus or
a nephrogenic
diabetes insipidus,
aside from the history
of the patient?
First thing you want
to do is you want
to fluid restrict
these patients, right?
Because again, if
we're fluid restricting
a patient, we would
expect that the
urine osmolality
would increase, that
they're going to hold
on to more water.
That's not
happening in these
patients with
diabetes insipidus.
So we would administer
desmopressin or ADH.
In central diabetes
insipidus, we would see
a dramatic increase in
the urine osmolality.
So we go up by more
than 100%. Whereas in
nephrogenic diabetes
insipidus, our urinalis
molality is really
going to be unchanged.
That makes sense
because in essential DI,
as we said, the body's
not producing enough
ADH. So giving it
ADH is going to fix
the problem. In nephrogenic
diabetes insipidus,
the body's producing
ADH just fine.
It's the kidneys that
are not responsive.
So giving more ADH is
not going to make a
difference in the
patient's urine osmolality.
So this is just a
graphic presentation of
what we discussed on
the previous slide.
When we have complete
diabetes insipidus,
as we see with the
maroon line, when we
administer desmopressin
our urine osmolality
will significantly
increase going from 175
to about 500 in this
diagram whereas if we
have nephrogenic
diabetes insipidus which
is the light blue line
when we administer
a desmopressin it
will not change our
osmolality of the urine
and to note the red
line is what should
happen normally right so
if we deprive the
patient of water for
hours the urine
osmolality should increase
by itself if the body's
working correctly.
How do we treat this?
As you might expect,
the same way we
diagnose central diabetes
insipidus is how we
treat it. So if
desmopressin corrects the
urine osmolality,
we give desmopressin
to patients with
diabetes insipidus, with
central diabetes
insipidus. For nephrogenic
diabetes is insipidus,
a little bit more
complicated. We want
to discontinue the
offending agent or
medication if it's
possible. So if lithium
is causing diabetes
insipidus, it can
actually be reversible.
But if the
tubular injury is
severe, which does
happen, it can be
irreversible for
those patients.
We want to put
these patients on
a low sodium,
low protein diet.
We want to give
thiazide diuretics as
well. This might sound
counterintuitive.
The effect is
presumably mediated
by a hypovolemia
-induced increase in
proximal sodium and
water reabsorption.
So this proximal
sodium and water
reabsorption diminishes
water delivery to the
ADH-sensitive sites
in the collecting
tubules, and that reduces
urinary output. So
a little bit
difficult, but thiazide
diuretics are indicated
in these patients.
And finally, for
patients taking
lithium, we can
give them milleride.
And the way this
works is going
to decrease the entry of
lithium into the
principal cells.
Let's look at another
case. We have a 32
-year-old male with
a history of high
blood pressure
hypertension presenting to
the clinic in August
with irritability,
muscle weakness for
the past three weeks.
So he's working in
construction and is
constantly thirsty,
which he attributes
to the high humidity
and the heat.
He's drinking more
than two gallons
of water a day,
and his coworkers
complain he's always
using the restroom.
The patient's not
taking any medication.
He denies tobacco,
alcohol, and illicit
drug use. There's
no fever nausea or
vomiting you get some
labs and the only
significant abnormality
is that the sodium is
148 which as we noted
is above the 145
threshold where we
diagnose hypernatremia
so what might
be going on in
terms of this
presentation
so you should be thinking
differential what's
your differential
diagnosis for
hypernatremia
You should be
thinking about
the diagnostic
testing that
should be done
for this patient.
And you should think
to yourself, what
would the diagnostic
testing show?
So for our patient,
the clinical scenario,
we have a patient
who has polyureum
polydipsia, so we should
probably be thinking
about diabetes insipidus.
We could also think
about an osmotic
diuresis or hyperglycemia
but it's less likely
that the patient
would have a normal
glucose as we know from
the previous labs
and while the patient
does have increased
insensible losses from
working in the heat
he is replacing them
adequately with sufficient
volumes of water
so diagnostic testing
we want to get a urine
osmolality urine
sodium concentration as
well these are going to
be helpful in determining
what the diagnosis
is. And what would
we expect these tests
to show, right? If the
patient was just not
consuming enough water,
we'd expect the urine
to be concentrated.
But in diabetes
insipidus, we
would expect a
dilute urine, so
a low urine
osmolality. Dave.
So we've gone
through some clinical
scenarios. Now,
let's move on
to a couple of
practice questions.
We have a 23-year
-old male presenting
to the clinic
complaining of polydipsia
with frequent large
volume urination.
Past medical history of a
posterior
pituitary tumor.
Physical exam,
we see dry mucous
membranes and
decreased skin tumor.
Laboratory testing
does not reveal
any evidence of
diabetes mellitus but
a urine osmolality
of 120 is measured
so which of the
following is the
most likely finding on a
desmopressin test
in this patient so
the answer here is a
urine osmolality to 600
milliosmoles per liter
let's talk about why
so a few feet a few
key things to focus in
on here first is the
complaint of polydipsia
right it's drinking
more water. So the
patient's not having an
issue consuming water.
Second is frequent
large volume urination.
He's got a posterior
pituitary tumor,
which as we talked about
before, is a common
cause of central
diabetes insipidus.
Dry mucous membranes
decrease skin turd or
signs of dehydration.
And lab studies don't
reveal any evidence
of diabetes mellitus.
so we shouldn't be
thinking that hyperglycemia
is the cause here
urine osmolality is
low which should not
be happening if the
kidneys are functioning
normally so our
patients dehydrated the
kidney should act to
concentrate the urine
but instead the urine
is dilute so we're if
we're administering
desmopressin in this
patient, we're thinking
it's either central
diabetes or insipidus
or nephrogenic
diabetes insipidus. Now
we'd probably lead more
towards central because
we have the posterior
pituitary tumor.
So the best answer
here would be that the
urine osmolality would
more than double.
So the only one
that would feature
that would be the
urine osmolality is
600 milliosmoles
per liter of choice.
Next question. 69
-year-old female
presents the emergency
department with
confusion. She lives
alone, no caretaker,
and is disoriented
and lethargic.
Physical exam, we
again see decreased
skin turgor and
dry mix membranes.
Sodium is elevated
to 165, BUN31
also elevated,
and crannin is
up at the upper
limit of normal.
Urine osmolality is
1,000 milliosmoles
per kilogram, and serum
osmolality is 300.
Which of the
following was the
most likely cause
in this patient?
So the correct
answer here is
lack of free
water intake. Why?
Well, we have an
elderly female
who lives alone,
no caretaker.
She's disoriented,
she's lethargic, and
she's dehydrated,
as evidenced by the
decreased skin to urine
dry mucous membranes.
We could also see that
her VUN is elevated,
which is another
sign of dehydration.
She's hypernatremic,
so sodium over 145.
Her urine osmolality
is high at 1,000.
This is the body
acting appropriately.
If you're dehydrated,
which the patient
is with dry mucous
membranes, the body
wants to concentrate
the urine, and that's
exactly what the
patient is doing here.
So if we have a
dehydrated patient who
has an elevated
serum sodium and the
elevated uranosmolality
of the body,
everything's working
fine and the patient is
just not consuming
enough water. So lack
of free water intake
makes sense here.
So in summary,
you should be able
to now explain
water balance
within the body. You
should be able
to illustrate the
pathophysiology of
hypernatremia, differentiate
the causes of
hypernatremia,
illustrate how to
diagnose and treat
hypernatremia
based off their
causes, and finally,
you should be
able to explain
diabetes and civics.
A few core
references here.
And finally,
please feel free
to submit feedback
via the link below.
Thank you so much.